Hi,let's start the welcome to build to those and fifteen.
...gopal...why I'm a corporate vice president of microsoft today I'm really
excited to talk to you guys abode the service fabric and its architecture for a
great part of my creative microsoft I've been working on this technology
...lead the conception incubation realization and the product position
of this technology we initially build this technology for use by or first
...services as...first by...of uses became successful be
...it's a good idea for to make it available to external
...as...and that actually brings us to this day where we...announcing
the job and availability of this technology when we actually started working on this
...that many of for first...for
reese's for repeatedly solving the same pod distributed systems problems and,
they in the process I think there was not only a bunch of needless
...was getting done but also that in the bugs are stuff that was done in
once of resource not getting leverage and of the service so we realized that we have an opportunity to
...foundation of distributed systems platform on which many of the
...services could build...that the...low-rate and build and that's all
...this technology?
This technology now I think is being made available to a
and third parties ...you know, this and stiki that is available if you go to the download
...you can actually download the sdk you can you know, create the
service fabric obligations ...scale minimized a single box
setup you can take those same applications that you actually develop on your box
and, move them to run as these in...when we actually offer this as a hosted
...offering and measure and couple of months you can also take the same obligations are
you're running a and move them on premises because we're going to ship this technology and
upcoming release of ...and sixteen so,
this is I mean this is a great moment and,
how also one of my colleagues and teammate who's actually go would,
come on,...come up and then do so presentations site
...us to do some demos us they come up and here is
the valuation slide?
What is...of my talk usually going to talk about how the application development
...the glowed...and, how...service fabric actually helps you build
...native applications based on the microsoft...architecture
...it and I'm going to talk briefly...how you can build scalable reliable and easily
manage microsoft uses using service fabric talk a little bit about you
...the system has been put together I...be kind of the
...little bit...I'll tell you...the...subsystems which are internally running within...service
...cluster and how they come together nicely to solve
...distributed systems problems so that
...can focus on the of the...logic and sort of...you know,
platform aspects and I will...summarize...the...
If not long ago ...for me it was true for many of my colleagues like, for example,
sequels or guys...I also worked...work in a your but it was
not long ago the interviewer actually happily developing a bunch of features we would
should these features every two years in a box product and then cycle used to big and what that
...with...rental...cloud because now not only are required invited school without
...developers today we are required to not only did
...features but also we have to take...off a whole bunch of stuff on that identified of this...like you have to think
...how do you billy also be useful...always the scalable from the sdp from the
get-go how do you actually solve and make sure that the...remains available
even in the presence of machine previews...for more importantly when you're patching that service?
How you actually think aboard how to build?
How do build scalable...do ...low latency
high throughput applications and all of these problem and think about data...data
...up you have to think about all these problems and, unfortunately you know,
if you start with the bid michael machines these problems of right in-your-face
so, what do not be nice for a platform to actually help you with solving
these problems so that we all can go to get back to actually developing features are
service specific logic that at a faster pace and help...the
...julia's and provide business value?
The globe.
Another thing that's actually changed for us is the flagged you know,
the architecture that via so used to in the past is not the architecture that you use for building
flowed native applications if you actually go and pecan to meet any of our workloads like
...br...bb ...on you actually see that they're not actually built in a tiered
we at all they're built...different way and the advantage of actually
building and adhered we are disadvantages you actually think...is that,
you know, you had you know, you could build all of these things...would put all of them in
...sort of machines and you actually depended on machines to provide the liability you typically random
on begun machinesyou actually could afford to take some
maintenance windows maybe order beak and where you could actually...on all the pieces of the software and
...them up and get them ready for the following monday but in the code world it's
not it's no longer that's not something that you can do because if you do that your customers will
...free from your business
are from your service so it is important for you to really think about the right-hand side of
this slide unfortunately so,...you know,
...start you build in a different way so that you can you get the benefits of that
and side by building on top of a platform and the way you actually think we're building
polled native apps in the modern base-two really
decompose the service components I into a lose me
a lou's be...in...interactive or standard protocol micro services
and again in a would it would be great if,
... the platform actually help you without and that's exactly where...fabric comes n?
So, when you areinvite this is true for us this is going to be
true for everybody who's thinking able buildinghigh skills are reese's when you're building a high
...you really need to think deeply able to scale reliability
and cost it is important that you design for scale from the get goals so you
want because the demand for your service is going to be variable...start off small and suddenly
...you know, pick up steam and then become very popular so you want to really design your
...such that you can run on a small...and to a large
...without actually you have to heavy having you go back and revisit
the architecture rebuild the service from scratch again so how do you do that I
think is something that you have to pay attention...at the beginning and not think about it as an afterthought after the
...being...deployed you also have to think aboard reliability, you know,
you really want to keep your service up and running you can't afford to have any maintenance windows
you really how to keep the service available even in the presence of failure
machine problem in the presence of machine failures but also when you're doing...patching of
the service an obvious whipping cost is very important again,
you know, as via is developers not long ago we thought ...developing code and
...features but that's no longer true because every...every piece of code that you
ride if it is more expensive to run that piece of code
...doing a good job so again you really need to think about how we can use
smart software on top of commodity hardware as opposed
to...hardware on top of a...machines to actually
...what...elaborately and scalability at the best
a economical value and these are the problems
dot vr for squad use of feast and
...be delivered a bunch of technologies for these people and that's where service
public came in and it actually I'm going to talk a little bit about some of the features
that's obvious fabric provides but...for building a
...used for doing the heavy lifting that is necessary for you to really build your services so that
they are from get goal in a scalable reliable and run at the best
prize that you can think of because
...of the things that we actually take pride in this particular system is that we have shaved
every possible I...every possible message in the system from so, that, you know, you get the best
cannot best price obviously, you know, if you build on top of this service you know, we are
shipping on windows today you can actually use seep cplus-plus of csharp apis
we're going to make this technology available online...and, you can and,
also expose them while they're programming models like java javascript so that,
you know, you have the choice of actually on running on the platform of your choice
of ways of your choice and you can also deployed?
On...your are on premises...third-party
uploads so by actually running on top of this platform you are, you know,
you have some choice in...you want to deploy your app or your service.
This particle slightly showing the number offor spotty services that are running on top
of leisure on...service fabric it is not that we, you know,
be conceived this technology are we build this technology last year and
they're giving you this technology this year we have I mean this
...more than a decade ago on this has been running and
...all of these services for the last five years more importantly
we're not actually we are giving you the exact same bits that are and
...so reese's in this sdk I'll talk about where it is different in a minute
...are not giving you a different washroom... less functional washroom
...diff and a call-in different copy of...core br...you guys you know,
...bunch of visual infrastructure itself runs on top of thisif
this service fabric doesn't do its job...bunch of a your its of goals
...similarly if the becomes most transactional
consistent databases are running on top of visual fabric we are the people so...fabric is the one which is doing all the
heavy lifting of replication reconfiguration managing the
lifecycle of every individual database dot actually you have running in...the on tens of thousands of
machines it actually is running consumer gates of reese's feature
...processing huge amounts...in a subscriptions and bingo...and,
it actually scales across three datacenters and recently they had...
outage of an entire datacenter and the soviets kept running and that's because of this
technology that there leveraging.
In the next.
Of...the rest of my talk I'm going to talk aboard whole.
Full-service fabric.
You know, that I'll pick a little bit under the...so,
that you guys can see...sorry I don't know why this.
This thing keeps moving I'm just going to keep going back and forth.
...basically I'm going to talk aboard hold...service...been put together
it's major subsystems so, that you get a little bit of an understanding of
hole the system works and,
along the way I'm actually going to talk aboard the exact problems that this these
different subsystems are going to solve and... hopefully motivate you on the role
...subsystems play in the system before I actually start talking aboard on
...parts of the system let me first actually talk
...precisely what we mean by a micro service if I'm asked to actually go and design
...internet scale surveys I'm actually going to...think aboard the
machines I'm going to think aboard my problem I'm going to think about what exact scenarios my
...is meant to solve and actually decompose the problem into a
sort of entities and then how those entities then I would think
...what is the scale characteristics of my service and I say this particular entity I want to scale
differently than this other entity so,
this decomposition...at the core of microsoft resource architecture you really
networking aboard machines unlike if you start from
...machines are virtual machines here you're thinking more at the
app layer and you're thinking about the app logical grady composer...
like make it run in such a way that I can upgrade different parts of the app
...actually anybody noticing that I'm...doing
and upgrade if you actually go and take a...the...you db that like sell-out eight
services that are microsoft...that are running obviously the biggest microsoft is there that's running
...the database service but there is a protocol gateway which is terminating tedious connections that
...a management endpoint which is actually...and ask for a database...the system it is the one
which actually goes on-call service fabric a I want...database...database for me so all these
...abuses that are running in the system they're all interacting with one another
...well-defined protocol so what exactly is a...service
...services...is a piece of code are piece of logic would also and,
its associated state and every...always in the system faster have
...so that you actually know portable...where exactly is my microsoft's my microsoft
reese's running you...tagger which machine it's running you talk about...my microsoft
ways so the naming system in service fabric actually use the
at responsible for actually determining...exactly a given instance of a microsoft
michael services running so that, you know, so, that you can go and talk to...so?
These micro services ...consistent a database obviously cannot lose
it stayed are not lose its transactional integrity because...a bunch of machines for
a task to remain consistent all the time and despite machine...
inside this despite a bunch...you actually find end up doing and at microsoft we
...obviously...doesn't actually appear in...you actually write a bunch of
cord and you say here is the code that is backing this or...and I want you to go...particular core and dot
...use what we actually put inside...container
...mean container here it's more general than the...all...and understand
...animal recently if you could be a process group inside running a job object
in many cases it's a bunch of processes, you know,
there's a sequels overwrought...watchdog process there's a bunch
...supporting processes and there's a full text indexing engine behind that sequels overwrought
eggs all these processes are manage as a single entity and they all maybe running
inside a container and
...typically each microsoft...you want to have a small team of developers
are responsible for it and they can move independent of other developers building others of uses in
the larger internet scale service so that's why this architectural entered
solve to increase...better reliability and by the scaleability because you can scale independent
...you can actually move independent and you get...our downgrade independent
...parts it...affecting other parts that are dependent on them because
if they're...well-defined protocols.
Obviously on...to types of microsoft reese's microsoft is which
...stateless and, microsoft...you...what exactly the stateless
...microsoft with obviously does not maintain any state are important
...micacious...that actually uses last beyond
...request on the responds that protocol service receives in the case of and, previous protocol
...some protocols which are which are stateful in the sense of, you know, they have some session
stayed but most of these protocols most of the protocols that you actually typically
...of the web...are protocol gateway substrate
...because...create and the way you actually...reliability for stateless services
...by maintaining and copies of them actually this is not that there's a hard problem
here from a distributed systems point of view but this is what actually everybody tells you
...in order to achieve scale just-born
build stateless services but who's going to solve the stateful, stateful problem obviously I think
...andwhen we were building this system we were actually thinking that this particular problem has to
be solved by us because we are the people who are actually supporting the database technology videos stateful
at the core so for stateful microsoft...on the other hand, you know,
you have speed that actually...at a...that...is
...you cannot afford to lose that state ...has to be a kernel of truth somewhere because if everything in the
entire woolly stateless you have nothing in the world because you have to have, you know,...waddle
...laying...somewhere so who's maintaining that
...that's where the stateful microsoft resource actually come into play and the way you
actually achieved reliability for state for microsoft resources by maintaining and copies of that
...obviously you want to maintain those and copies of the state
and a consistent manner because you really have to think about how your updating
...mutating that...and the system has to give you those guarantees that the and copies of
state your maintaining
...indeed consistent...you be attribute I'll talk a little bit about how we achieve that consistency?
And, you know, example stateful microsoft...are...or databases and, you know,
documents and, you know, user state user...tools
on other things so with that in mind I'm going to invite my friend my teammate to,
come on, board and actually talk...statefull stateless michael service because I'm now
...guys on a journey of making the sys...the system
starts with a simple thing and how it becomes complex as you go down ...on the
...on the path in this particular case...stateless microsoft ways it's nothing
but a visual object we just really moving in space it does have state and,
that's date...is a location eighties and, the past ten locations baited had
beam and we will show you how that state ...state stables microsoft reese's
and other shoulder-to-shoulder running I really do some failures and see...it goes?
What we want so, here's an example of a stateless
micros service in this case the micro services an object floating around in this
space this state of the art is represented by the current position as well
as the history which is represented by...the tail saw here is a
...explorer this is a tool that we offer as part of the sdk which allows you to
visualized manage and monitor your cluster so,
what I'm going to do is that here I have that
service which is the stateless service that stateless service
has one instance and it is running on node three as you can see here
some more input this to auto refresh so we have one instance of that service running on
node three and what I'm going to do is basically restart node three?
So,...what happens to the instance
that is here as well as the object so,
as you can see that.
The as a so in this particular case actually what ripple data is
...just to give a machine think of it like that and that machine on a
...the system actually dictated the...landed actually is going to and,
figure out where to place a realize that this particle microsoft
...fail and it's going to restart...the ...on a different machine ...and.
...see it, come on, you can see that it actually came
back but unfortunately I had to put on my glasses because I'm getting old.
The what I think maybe you guys didn't notice is that when it actually started on
a machine this particular microsoft has lost its state embossed
...position it had been and, the last and positions...being in so don't actually went back to some,
you know, of the position rated actually to apply for to...because...
Because.
...go back to my slides.
But, the system did solve the problem of detecting that the machine has gone
...and actually figuring out a particular instance of a
...uses fade and...it somewhere else audited do dot and,
that's where the failure detection problem for the system can't even for stateless microsoft
...which we think are the easy ones compared to the stateful ones
there is a hard distributed systems problem which is a failure detection problem and that's what you know,
these to subsystems actually provide in-service
fabric obviously we have a transport...you know, if you're building...distributed system you have to have
machines talking to one another all of this is not running on a single machine so,
how do we actually have these communication establish between machines we
obviously use this thing called transport it certainly does lots of security it
does a bunch of stuff but and...the date that's actually not that hard other than making sure but, you know,
it is...you'll?
Scope rules and a bunch of other staff the more important characteristic it has is
...best effort it doesn't
actually any give you any guarantee to layers of over but it is going to deliver the message.
We can be could have easily use tcp you'll be...use...tcp...our in
our in-service fabric at the moment that is a...because we get the fragmentation...be assembly
easily because...that for us...more importantly...the tcp...whether you as realize that the
modern chips particularly under the messages are very small that you can actually fit in a single frame
it is actually more faster...more perform interact with them tcp that...of course,
you know, the special cases like broadcast of other things
where are you reviews useful all but in a typical
...datacenter network tcp actually performed very well because you have to...offload
...and, a bunch of stuff that you actually can benefit from on top of dot
...the best effort layer is what we call the federation this is where you
know, I will introduce the notion of a cluster so in absence of the federation
what you see in a datacenter invite if you don't have...fabric this is what you get so
...for...map of any other data...you go and ask for a bunch of machines you
get a bunch of machines what do what can you do with this machines...or let me
start and we build this or how do I know about this machine being part of the sister all...
did this machine fail I mean all of these problems are in front of you and you know,
we don't know-how to solve and every...starts ...from the from the bottom of this bag and
...so in other words just having a bunch of machines with the great always
that you law is not enough to build a service you really need higher-level
...higher-level platforms on which you can actually
...your service specific logic so that you do not
...solve any of these problems not only that you actually network plank in
...of our developers do not think it would machines but think about their
...their packages...of the...and how to...maintain
...elaborately and that's...reese's user that four-bit meeting available so what happens is
...service fabric cluster comes up you know, it basically goals are determines what machines are part of
the clusterand, then at this point of time
it knows what machines are in the system and what machines of...information is fairly
...that machine as for this is exactly the layer at which the failure of the...as microsoft
resource determined by the system so that you could determine all machine died
so I need to really figure out something to do have to...to do something with it and that's all we figured it
order mood at obviously that's not enoughfor state fall by that useful stable that's good
enough how does the system actually detect these failures I think in our system I'm
giving it a fairly high-level every machine as an identity and there's a bunch of machines because
every mission as an identity that some...sort of machine that are considered
libraries in this particular slider time pi-zerowe have
...for machines five machines reduced...the...or eighty-three
...sixty-four for p and forty-six at time?
T...few things happen in the system is
...is very dynamic I'm there is nothing that you can control here...nodes for a...of this
...sixty-four and sixty-one arrived I can show you
that as this thing is happening the system is are the...and it
is not that-you there is no static knowledge in the system the system doesn't
have, you know, this one place where it is maintaining membership...all
...distributed system...the you cannot you can go and asses mission tell me,
you know, whether this machine is...comes back and answered by not
doing a lookup table on something but I by actually doing some distributed systems work
...needs to go and tell you...that machine doesn't does exist and...indeed up so,
after by a bunch of you know, protocols which is modern protocols it actually comes back and
...of, you know, I have no figured out that machine...and sixty-four
...and new machine sixty-one...and there may be...noone looking for this
...assuming that they're already the activated because I'll
talk aboutan machine lifecycle management in our system but this is
...if these machines have failed like...of stateless michael service...here is the layer
...which we detected...machine prelude...and, that's...the system reacted.
Okay, so, what exactly running in our foster obviously, you know, the services that
are users of...or customers...of rhythm but there's a bunch of
system services also running and many of these of stateful...all of them are stateful there's a
...manager service which is actually watching every state?
Which is watching everymicrosoft
is that has been provision and running in the cluster and seeing...user...up user running...it
...and, when it detects failure to...the one which is causing trade-offs to happen
there's a cluster manager service which is watching we just doing lifecycle management operations
...you want obligated a cluster manager is the one that comes into play and says
okay it is one that carries or those lifecycle management operations naming I already talked
...every microsoft...a name and you want to really
locate its and point dynamically at runtime you...that I'm going to scale because this
soulmate across coming in the system that, you know, the naming is the one web those things are happening
...image stories where every time you provision piece of code
...configured data into the system
image store services where we actuallystore all that data it's all the all these services
...if that all the...never lost?
Unless, you know, the and lackluster was gone and I said in the case of
...these clusters...actually spanning tree datacenters...datacenters that you want in
the encoder like...the...three data servers and, I can...
You can actually...and just to show you guys that, you know,
these services are indeed running on your scale
minimize development box you can see that is available...services running...
a cluster manager this an image store a bunch of naming service by the way because naming
serviceis also partition I'll I'm going to talk
...for scaling old partitions so you can actually take microsoft
...are not only can you say I want and copies of that running you can also say I want to partition it so that
the partition it by range partitioned by name or whatever you whatever scheme that you
...so that it gives of naming service you can see that
...multiple partitions in this case...three partitions that are actually running?
So, that's basically the I wanted to show you guys, you know,
the service fabric explore that's actually part of the system...trips as part of the as the case so you
guys confided up and you know, visualize your clusters.
Okay, so, far we talked about failures we talked about stateless
micro services...the time for us to really think about how do we do state and,
that's where the elaborately subsystem comes and it is the one that is you know, taking...of the state
aspects of the system why are statefull microsoft resource important and,
I'm pretty sure I think many of us you-know-who are
...in the past I've seen this particular pattern repeated multiple times, you know,
you basically start off you know, you take your app...you capability
and peers you start with the front and then you go and put all your business logic in this
...and, you say stateless and because these media can collapse any time you
go and put all your hard and...in back...databases then you start thinking well,
what happens if I want reliable communication between my front-end
and my meteor what do I do I will introduce a bunch of q so I put it in the
...on the front and I retrieved from the...on the on the
mid-air now you say I want communication reliable communication between might between components and
...now let me go and...between those guys then come back and say
all I really need to think...my databases cannot really performyou know,
my...slow my rights...that we would
...layer...how you put your caching layer now...all
...partition system how caching layers I can't think about transactions let me actually
...to manage all these transactions on some ahold that my transactions my system
is consistent and this is what we all phased...
this is where this system comes into play and...a very complex system I can't even
reason...the correctness of this system if you go and ask in any computer science guy would
...is transactions consist you know, maybe...failure doesn't happen that failure doesn't happen it's...
been but that is never the case and datacenter bad things happen and we assume awful things
happen to us in many times so it is important for us to really paying how
can be simplify this, you know, architecture via all familiar with your all grew up with
something that is more cogent most a simple are and easy-to-understand at the
same time guarantees the correctness that we all want to have?
And, there comes in stateful michael services in this world I...you can see that the
...the becomes much simpler you basically have your front-end invite in some cases you get our the
front-end but...you don't need that you can your stateful
...obvious can actually terminate implement because itself but let's assume that you...a state
...a...internet protocols and then it goes and talks to
is statefull michael service in this particular case you're
...right next to that state of course your partitioned it and, you know, I'll talk about this...transactions
down the line but not in this dog but the point I'm trying to say is that now you
...stayed...dykstra your cord and you can now use a.
All you leads are highly have very low latency sorry and,
your rights are very fast.
And, partitions or first-class.
And, I don't know-how many of you guys have actually gone and see I mean I'm sure you guys have seen what mark actually
...we have transactions built into the system you can actually fault
in different data structures in our system
...actual...transactions to do updates on those transaction so you are really
writing code that you're familiar with when you're writing any...omit...
State of what we what used to called business logic core where you...a bunch of data structures and
you go and do a bunch of updates and then you go and put it in the database now, you know,
longer have to think about it like that you just say hey I want to...ina...a bunch of data structures
let me use my transaction update all these data structures and then if I come it will
always stay committed if I'm if I aborted...what if I do...the system automatically takes care of the
...for you and then the system proceeds with this architecture becomes very simple,
you know, longer have so many moving parts you are now
...loyalty be pod the most important cuticle internet
...part of your system has best performance lowest
low...throughput and low latency and
...analytics parts of the system where you actually periodically...data to go into
...store so-and-so that you can do other analytical jobs on it like map reduce jobs you
...do that later this is all I think the modern told native
...development happens this is what we believe...fabric
...will happened on the line if not knowledge will happen as...
Okay, so,
we actually already talked about the stateless and we showed the visual object which
is moving in this space which has stayed but, that state got lost and be
...machine on...running now...make the same stateless object stateful and
...see how the states or wise if we...
Throw...particle is represented by a statefull
application you can see that it has a primary and secondary which gopal
...talk ...all sorry use five.
Ok, so, this four-star was the one that we saw the stateless this
is the statefull ...
micros service the stateful micros service you can see that the primary of this
services running on node one and,
what I'm going to do is that all go look at...the...one?
Going-to...service figure out which...just
...posit so you can you guys can see that this is all you know, the code gets run in the system, you know,
all the code all microsoft...a school you sipping and a bunch of
...packages which maybe running inside job objects
are containers but we know exactly which microsoft uses running in which
...package whether it's...part on the machine on midgets running that...sell the are not so that we can
do, you know, we can make sure that the system is running how the all the time.
And, okay, so.
I'm going-to go ahead and kill the primary process
...look what happens here in this region as well as look what happens to
...to the object.
there you can see that compared to what happened with the stateless microsoft is obviously thing
...because it was like entire machine going down here the system...door very
fast because when we're building stateful microsoft reese's we're not actually talking aboard,
you know,...recovery audio you go...this damping into some
...stared and you...state somewhere else in some cases of...like...a
...database you have gigabytes in some cases tens of gigabytes
our hundreds of gigabytes of data if you do recall you will sit there for thirty minutes before
this thing happens so in how does...guarantee these things because it as these hot stand
...you just saw...standby inaction instantaneous
...lower of the system is because all the other databases are all assist all the data
up and recovered and running and they're just doing very simple operations
...just applying mutations so they're not actually consuming that much cpu and,
they are actually working and when the
...what happens they just decor and that's all we build
these systems and that's the beauty of statefull microsoft reese's you get that latency
characteristics you get this nice figured you know,
characteristics and you get a whole bunch of simplicity by building at on these concepts?
So, that's the demo stateful microsoft racedoing time.
Okay, so, how did we actually do this actually an invite you have seen
in vibe explores...service fabric explorer?
You know, we maintain replica us of every statefulmichael...we maintain
a replicas and, we have this distinguish the replica called the primary
replica which is actually the one which is receiving client operations and,
it is the one which is figuring if
...a lead I'll talk about...the one which is applying these state mutations it is realizing
...mutations for you guys who...computer
...of the and applying them in order on other places and we
actually?
Maintain rewrite...on so it is are extremely...tolerant I'm in.
This other aspect of statefull microsoft is I don't know but I have time to go through itissue is
...tolerance you know-how many of your requests
...ninety nine-point nine percent bile are actually terminating
...an extremely low latency and you really need to really think about if
...in the treated architecture I...every request us to go and...even if individual
...intuitive components of those layers actually have ninety nine-point nine
reliability the war all system if you compose them together in
...ninety nine-point nine three times you get ninety nine-point some...something like that so
...less people think that I have a really great system but you really have to build...
systems in order to build dale...system again it goes back to building these...and,
the system is actually doing all of this...work.
Under the for you when you just basically did hey I...my data structure
...transaction and all of this stuff is right in your...you know,
regular...complete...it could be...cplus-plus code csharp or java
court or whatever we think we can come up at but,
you're right including complete logic in your favorite language using your favorite framework and the
system is doing the underlying grunge work to take care of in the your needs.
This is a straight-a stateful microsoft within...action,
... the system has obviously so far in this in this talk
I talked about single instance microsoft uses the best
stateless of straightforward obviously the system...much higher density than
...so, if you go back and sequel has one-point-two million databases
running on hundreds of thousands of machines and pencil those...machines you know,
the hundreds of thousands of processes running on those machines and the system
is watching carrying are looking at taken care of
...every individual database with the ninety nine-point nine latency that
...problem and reliability...promised or customize
the system is built to go and deal at that level now.
As you can see the in
their multiple replica as just like...in the gives a state a system services where you know,
at the cluster has multiple stateful microsoft uses and...all replicating to
their cohorts in some otherpart of the cluster this is all the system works I mean I'm giving
this little baby but I will also show you something else on hold the cluster actually
gets visualized so what happens when a primary replica receives
...from the cost from its clive if let's assume that...only doing it and, they read but it's going
...read it just can service attributes it doesn't even talk to...replicas
...people will talk about...there is primary secondary quorum so what we are building these replicated state missions
...length a slightly different from what you would know about axles machines are
because these...here there's a distinguish replica because we want leads to dominate gets
...dominate in any michael service compared to rights and you want leads
...you have eighty percent...seventy percent...fifty puts on read uone those
...to be satisfiability fast and you want to pay the cost
invite and if you're not careful and you don't have distinguish replica...you know,
you will not be able to of user
...so that's what the system actually guarantee there's a whole bunch of details here but when
...write happens as opposed to a...the primary actually figures,
you know, the transaction come...and we figure out what has all been updated we update the
...those rights...is...second movies come back and the acknowledge
...of them we actually commit the transaction on the primary and then
we respond bag and then the client generates and...the some...generates and activities
...if one of the...slow...later the system
...transactions already...will do nothing with that so this is also you know,
the system is very...with its...doing the bested...on the rights and, it's
...dollar and it's extremely scalable now?
In this thing this is all wonderful and
great and if I give you a probability of machine failures and if you don't do anything with this replica
set all these replicas will die so it's not enough for you to just do core alms
...or replication and other things you need to really take care of failures that
...and while these things are happening and that is this slide we have to
reconfigure these replica sets,... just like you know, we showed in the case of statefull michael service we can
be primary and the system actually reacted and promoted one of the second
...as a primary the way...build is your...the primary
...allocate a new primary and white-out the system is up and running
...at the lead use replication factor in this public is we
...running with for and what happens is that in all let's say that
pay replica that died, you know,...you know, it became back ical while it's happening and
of secondary diedthen the systems at all it's a secondly that died it again don't shifts to...reduce
replication factor for a temporary thing I mean the this reconfigurable knobs in the system
...starts running in the meantime one of the primary that
...comes back into the system we detect that all the system the system detects
...this particular replica was a primary?
But, deduce fairly
...if it's fairly, you know, close to what is the stayed in the current system and without this
prior when it before he died it catches up whatever state updates that particular
...primary fade and makes it the secondary now we're back to
for replication factor and if it ought to if it sees that...something called replica
restart we duration and...the...passes which is configure rubble the
...ok I'm not going to get another replica into the system let me go and build a new brand-new replica guide
...on the side catches that guy up?
then when it's fairly caught...brings it into the...set now we're back to five replication
factor...and obviously all of these things, you know, I'm showing a nice animation
...real system these things while you're doing a primary election
the new primary may die while you're doing a secondary and of the primary made by the lots of bad things, you know,
...can have can happen in the system so
building this thing is not for faint of the hard you really think and,
it's not it's not the annoyed these are harp and obviously if you put our mind
...anything we can go and solve this problem but do we really need to solve this problem
repeatedly do we really can't be leverage andstand on the shoulders of the jade whether it's
other whether somebody else so this is how we belt has a don't want to...have every
the first...going build these things I'm even though we...on?
Trust me I think we...build...of all these things and, many of them are bugs.
They don't...on you bug fixed in one service doesn't make it to the other...so we actually ended up
building service fabric to go and solve these problems ones for all and we have been running
...for five years and now we the time for us to really make it broadly available.
I remember I talked about a single services stateful microsoft resource...michael service and again
...statefull rs
...can be partition in this particular case I'm actually showing you guys...of
...so, when the system says I will need to create a service you can say I want a
...stateful microsoft ways of ten partitions each replicated three-time
...replication and...the system will take care of all of that in this popular case it's creating a
four-bit replicated partition of the state-to-state
...michael service ...the firstpartition...a second
...third partition...some point it...the partition that you need while and then
...this...doing this one of the machine fails remember what's between the two
...look, at the green partition the green partitions primary
walls on-the-field machine the system react fast?
...in on the federation comes and says okay this machine
...the system heals itself and,
then comes back and says there was a primary partition green primary partition that was living on this
...machine let me go and alec one of the secondary...the primary so-you
does done that and now says all there...some bunch of second is that we're running on
...machine and these orange partition...partition
are actually sending replicated operations which are going into mapping the remember the
added now says let me stop those things and now the system is actually fairly record
although...running with...replication factor in the case of, you know,...of these
a partitions now we realizes that all its...and it starts building new replicas assuming that we got
...probably duration of fast and then it goes back and now the system
has completely heal from this machine failure and
...actually drive home the point we will actually show you a cluster monitor
...this thing running in the system which is what...eight yes.
You can see on the right-hand side on the left side.
So, here is a stateful partition micros
service which has multiple partitions and this is the visualization of it.
Here is the cluster monitor that issuing where the primaries and
secondary...pleased so, you can see here
for this particular partition the primary is here and the two-x two-second...
notify and node...on this one the primaries on node three and the
secondary on this as well as the secondary on the on another node?
So, you can see that all of these things are...war in the system and
you can visualize these things you can, you know, we have explorers we have some
on some built-inservices that will tell you what is running where and.
Which...
Now you know, so, far I talked about stateless...single instance stateless michael servicing instance
...micro...and then I talked about how you can partition them so that you get a
large number of instances and now you actually
your application assayactually describe right at the beginning is not a single michael...a bunch of
...services that you put together and
deploy them together into the cluster and that's what this particular slide is actually showing
...animation so-if
...those containers and places those microsoft uses and this and more importantly
you can create multiple instances of this state this a
application learning in the cluster and you can do ab testing you can have your
goal customers go-to one instance of the application and which is more a
...a ...a lower twitch than, you know, bleeding edge
...where you really are doing no more features
...in updating them faster and you without affecting your goal customer so you can actually
...instances of these applications running in the
...in the cluster inside if you actually go and ask for
...visual database we give you a set of databases those databases...really
district from the databases in a more in the new...you db you go-go compared to the databases
...customer each customer can say I want update my database to the later
...also reese's sequels or...the customer...I...back on my got my
...base so we are giving all these flexibility we build all these things so that,
you know, you again once again can take these things can be taken care of for-you?
Comes the application lifecycle so we talked about how we provide a bunch of
reach runtime capabilities to microsoft reese's and,
this particular case that's right I mean obviously that's great that's
useful but we also need to provide additional capabilities so that are in a for...workloads
...for the null unless you guys will be able to go and.
I know do lifecycle management operations on your microsoft...you want to really
provision and apply in all contribute michael services you really want to upgrade
michael services without affecting without affecting other microsoft reese's and,
without losing any availability you want to met...michael services, you know, whether that how the are not
there's a built-in health system in the system and you want more importantly you want to
do have guarantees in the system...many times you actually know this by now we
...you guys are probably realize that this is a highly consistent system you can
relaxes consistency but by the by default you get a
highly consistent system because without consistency is very hard to
reason the correctness let's say you're trying to upgrade the protocol that a particularmicrosoft
is implements in order to do that upgrade you need to go and make sure...that a
microsoft used to support...protocol in the new protocol as well as you know,
upgraded it's blind so that this start talking new protocols but you cannot go and removal
that support for the word protocol until all its clients
...are ...services and also...also been...how you get
the guarantee in the system again the system comes back and says one through those finish the guaranteed
says there is no war code running in the system so what you do or what we do is do a two-face
upgrade you actually have the war protocol implement the new protocol how the service...support
both those protocols and then go back and do other configure
...switch to using only the new protocol and it...you actually remove that
...so that so you actually can manage
in the life-cycle of...as
...lasting for years in some cases tens of years and you still want to be able to reason
about this system all I know that this particular version of the code is running in the system and I know that
the system is guaranteed to me that no waller version of the code that is running I mean if you have
...hundreds of thousands of machines...keep track of these things all of these things
are to be automated so next I'm going to show you guys?
The actual
...behind these services you can actually see that this visual objectis actually
a...an actor and it doesn't on activate method it starts it takes
...life...and the...and we just a
...the timer...it actually goals and moves itself here is a
...more remember in vone core...saying...to rotate so we
be and the...status...ball I mean in the case of I mean
there's transaction pieces reliable services and there's another api called reliable object is
...objects api you can think...in terms of objects
...virtual actors and you can actually go and build your
...programming model you like you can be your code on top of it and,
the aps...simple you know,
you get activated you get the activated you have a bunch of timers that you can actually
...as needed...you can actually...for find reckless...you're done and here in this
public is the primary speaking and actually updating the location of the object and if
you go to the movement...you can see that?
The at the end if the rotate these true it's adding
attend degree rotation to the object and if you go back and.
You can see that all these things are actually not rotating so these are all running
version one of the code we are now going to go to washington to of the code.
This is...rotate is falls
...to rotate this group.
And, we'll do an upgrade and you will see that the system will go
through the upgrade without losing availability and...of the...you'll see these objects rotator.
Some gloom the start the grid we can watch the
of grid progress in the cluster monitor as well as in the explore
solve keep both of these here and as gopal mention are wild
...grid is happening you will see that the system doesn't lose
this state which means that this objects that are there they will
...momentarily and restart from the same position remember the state of the object was
its current location and the history if the system where to lose the state
you can you would you would see the object jumping all...all you can see that it actually went through
a bunch of updated actually took a bunch of code packages...and to the upgrade
...switch to the other one and I'll will come back to this no,
this is where?
You know, this is what is happening in the
system you have a as a package which is already running if...
is already running and we want to sorry?
So, this was this is the my...of microsoft
is running on the system and we decided to convert the yellow one from
...blue one which is...and now we want to...what the system is does is it
goes and carefully orchestrated upgrading each of those yellow one without actually
...losing availability always maintaining core alms so all the time the rights are going
through and the system...up all the time and,
it also monitors all these...so that if anything goes bad...back.
They, yeah, so.
So, now you can see that...some of these objects are rotating you can see that one of them is
actually rotating if you can see that as update is going through obviously these
update your be very careful...these are not willy-nilly...create and instances
...I can do that very easily...stateless I can easily created liked
hundreds of instances when you're dealing with statefull staff you really have to make sure
...there in some cases obviously these objects are simple objects but in some cases like databases
your gigabytes of speed you really need to think of old how you carefully
orchestrate these things so that you never lose availability this is not in a real-world you know,
you this stateful objects are very complex objects and they have lots of state
it's not a demo thing that I can go...has been of like hundred instances...instances you know,
when the system is balancing them it's actually doing it very carefully we told you actually losing
availability, you know, but, I...I'm doing upgraded it's not that the most important thing for
me use forty-two really complete and I want to completed in an automatic way...told me...
holding it but I want to do it in a very easy way so now you can see that
this...the cost update
is going through and it bringing on more and more the thing what are the last ud and,
you can see that it's got remember I told you how it's going...time or update domain at a time
...failure domain you can see that it's computed...one...and then it's actually and,
I'll actually it's done is that...so
yeah, it's completed so now you would see that all of them are actually rotating?
So, this is what we are build the system and, there's one other thing which.
I want to talk abode which is the test ability all of this is wonderful but,
you know, that...will always of bugs
...you write code you want to have some amount of failures
happening in the system all the time and you can actually dial-up or dialed
...those the rate of those failure so the system actually comes with the prebuilt
cure-all service which is actually
...own and killing processes killing machines
...machines all...very bad things and...dial on a variety of
...disease-causing and you can dial them up...them...and
ensure that you know, your services running bug free most of the time so this is all you
vetoed the bugs before, you know,...hate your customers...there will be some bugs that will be
there and production systems but hopefully by the time it hits the production your
redid or most of the bug and you also have the key also is running in your production system so that
...reading...bug as the appear you rather
...them sooner than later so you can actually deployed the service on by the way
...lowered also uses...and you can actually go and
deploy and in this particular slide you can see that...stability
use actually causing a bunch of failure modes and as those failures are happening
...let me see what had to put all my glasses the problem of for...
The agency...activated code packages it is killing machines that clearly it's
...processes and then as it's doing its job you know,
the cluster in the cluster visualize...what's happening in the system so
again the system comes with a bunch of prebuilt services you can choose to build in
a deploy them like you...this putting together looks like...and...and then the system continues to operate.
That brings me to.
And, obviously there's a lot more interesting stuff here.
You know, brings me to look and of my talk you know, this.
We built this service ...that we build this
platform this distributed systems platform primarily for force parties ...us
parties you use a bunch of low-level apis in our system.
We realize that, you know, some of those aps most of them are native apis...have a bunch of
...more...a bunch of code in the system if you actually downloadable installed a bunch of
...as well so the amount of code that these guys...using the aps...but using
the low-level apis we thought that we actually in order to make the system more approachable we started working
...a year-ago building higher-level programming models and higher-level apis on
...the system.
The core has been bigger long long-time but the stuff that viet building on
top these approachable programming models
are approachable apis and the visual studio integration you still...maybe some
rough edges that you guys will encounter as you guys are using but we are going to fix all of them and,
you know, and, the qualities bait so it is all this, you know,
higher-level little things or these this parameter name dried
...confusing or did actually do that I'd thing and maybe there's a bug
...also so the key is that we big the core we're giving you
theaccess to these tobits with the much...more approachable
...programming model as well as tooling integrations where you may see some
...ridges but, you know, if you guys user providers feedback via
our and we are going to ship this even on a weekly with them
and we will want to take you guys to production by the end of this year if plausible so,
please go download the...bill apps on top of this and,
give us feedback and that will help us make the system better?